Guie to the Justice Carlos R. Moreno papers M1855
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Justice Carlos R. Moreno papers
1994-2009
M1855
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
3.5 Linear feet (7 manuscript boxes)
Papers pertaining to Justice Moreno's professional career, including notes, correspondence and two binders that have memos, correspondence and newspaper articles that span Justice Moreno's career. Also included are six VHS cassettes, paper copies of e-mails, and a complete set of speeches archived on one CD.
Moreno, Carlos Roberto, 1948-
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by Justice Carlos R. Moreno to Stanford University, Special Collections in 2011.
Biography
Carlos R. Moreno was admitted to the California Bar in 1975 and began practicing law with the Los Angeles City Attorney’s office in the same year. In 1979, Moreno left the City Attorney’s office for the private sector where he began practicing at Kelly, Drye & Warren, and remained there until his appointment by California Governor George Deukmejian to the Municipal Court of the Compton Judicial District in October 1986. Following his years of service on the municipal Court he was appointed by California Governor Pete Wilson to the Superior Court of Los Angeles County in October 1993. On July 31, 1997, President William Jefferson Clinton nominated Justice Moreno to a federal judgeship on the United States District Court for the Central District of California and received confirmation by the Senate on February 3, 1998. Justice Moreno later resigned from his lifetime appointment as a federal judge upon being nominated to the California Supreme Court by California Governor Gray Davis in 2001. After serving ten years on the California Supreme Court, Justice Moreno submitted his resignation on January 6, 2011 intending to retire from his position as an Associate Justice effective February, 28, 2011. After his retirement from the California Supreme Court he returned to private practice with the law firm of Irell & Manella, LLP.
Carlos Roberto Moreno was born in Los Angeles, CA on November 4, 1948 to immigrant parents. Moreno’s maternal grandfather, Carlos Brücklmaier, was a German citizen who immigrated to Mexico in the late 1800s. Moreno’s mother, Maria Luisa Brücklmaier, is of German Mexican descent who immigrated to Los Angeles, CA from Mexico in the 1920s. She married José Hidalgo during the Great Depression of the 1930s and had two daughters, Lupe, and Gloria. Hidalgo later abandoned his wife and daughters. She was assisted in raising her children by her dedicated brother, José Brücklmaier, who eventually would become a mentor to Justice Moreno. Luisa later met Jesus Govea Moreno during World War II and they had three sons, Peter, William and Carlos, who was born in 1948. After World War II the family moved to Solano Canyon near Chavez Ravine in Los Angeles, CA. Chavez Ravine was eventually razed for the construction of Dodger Stadium in the late 1950s. His mother Maria Luisa passed away in 1975 at the age of 66.
Carlos Moreno had fond memories growing up in the Chavez Ravine neighborhood which was predominantly a community of working class Italian and Mexican American residents. Moreno grew up around family, cousins, nephews, and nieces. Moreno, a native Spanish speaker, excelled academically at Lincoln High School where he developed leadership skills with famed educator/activist, Sal Castro. Castro gained notoriety for organizing the 1968 city wide walk-outs protesting unequal academic access in the Los Angeles Unified High School District. Moreno was known in the neighborhood for assisting relatives with submitting the necessary paperwork to the proper agencies, a task that for Spanish speaking residents could be arduous. In high school, his teachers motivated him to read extensively, become a good writer, and study the arts. After attending the opera while in high school, Moreno became a lifelong fan and singer of opera. Moreno graduated from Lincoln High School in 1966 and received a scholarship to attend Yale University, where he received a B.A. in political science in 1970. Moreno returned west and attended Stanford University and graduated with a Juris Doctor in 1975.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence and photographs of Justic Morreno, articles and clippings regarding his career and materials relating to his court cases. Included also are speeches and an oral history.
Separated Materials note
Two folders have been removed from the collection: FBI investigation records and Deed of Gift to Stanford University. These items are restricted until the year 2050.
Moreno, Carlos Roberto, 1948-; California--Politics and government--21st century--Sources; California. Supremem Court--History--21st century; Judges--California--Sources; Law--California--History--Sources
- Congratulation letters on appointment to Federal Bench: 1998. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Senate Judiciary Committee Questionnaire (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Nomination and Appointment to CA Supreme Court (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Congratulatory Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Contacts (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letters of Recomendation (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Memorandum: Sotomayor Legal Decisions (Box 2, Folder 1)
- CA Supreme Court: Commission on Judicial Appointments. Ocotber 1, 2001. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Administrative Office of The U.S. Courts (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence Rleated to federal Judgeship. 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Federal Court Appointment Letters of Support (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence related to Federal Appointment (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Yale Medal: November 19, 2009. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Various Newspaper clippings (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Retirement from CA Supreme Court (Box 2, Folder 9)
- List of Moreno Opinions: 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Biography Summary (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Various Photographs: One picture with Educator, Sal Castro on deabte team (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Commission on Police Repression (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Summary of Court Cases (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Electronic Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Court Case Summaries (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Court of Appeals Decision (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Court of Appeals Case Summary (Box 3, Folder 6)
- L.A.Times Article on Justice Moreno (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Courtly Comaraderie. 10-12-2009. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Yale Award (Box 3, Folder 9)
- The Recorder: Article, May 22, 2009. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- The Modesto Bee: June 25, 2009. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Table of Contents: Moreno News Clips (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Obama to talk court nomination with Senate leaders (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Feinstein Pushes Two Hispanic Judges (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Moreno Said To be on Supreme Court Short List (Box 3, Folder 15)
- NY Times: May 20, 2009. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- From Barrio To the Ivay League and Back (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Sacramento Report: July 20, 2010. (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Profile of Justice Moreno (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Governor Press Release: 8-1-2001. (Box 3, Folder 20)
- LA Times: Chavez Ravine., Play. 9-24-2006. (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Concurring and Dissenting Opinion by Moreno (Box 3, Folder 22)
- LA Times: September 26, 2009. Moreno Raises Profile. (Box 3, Folder 23)
- The Recorder. July 24, 2009. History is on my Side. (Box 3, Folder 24)
- LA Times: May 16, 2008. Gay Marriage Ban Overturned. (Box 3, Folder 25)
- A Man in The Middle: The Insider story on Justice, Carlos Moreno. (Box 3, Folder 26)
- U.S. District Court, Southern District of California (Box 4, Folder 1)
- CA Supreme Court Newspaper Articles (Box 4, Folder 2)
- CA Supreme Court Newspaper clippings (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Personal Data Questionnaire, Judicial Appointments (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Court Case Summary (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Law Dragon, Letters of Publication. April 2006. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Various Newspaper Articles on CA Justices (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Various Newspaper Clippings (Box 5, Folder 3)
- The Recorder: March 19, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Moreno in Action, with various articles (Box 5, Folder 5)
- The Los Angeles Daily Journal: June 5, 1997. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Los Angeles Daily Journal (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Justice Moreno Speeches 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Responses to American Bar Association: 1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Letters, re: appointment to the Los Angeles Superior Court (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Letters supporting appointment to court (Box 6, Folder 2)
- LA Superior Court, Installation of Judges. March 18, 1994. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- CA Supreme Court: Newspaper Articles (Box 6, Folder 4)
- CA Supreme Court Appointment Newspaper clippings. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Various Newspaper Articles of Justice Moreno (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Metropolitan News Enterprise (Box 6, Folder 7)
- The Recorder: A Judges Journey, October 8, 2001. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- The Recorder and LA times Articles (Box 6, Folder 9)
- CA Supreme Court newspaper coverage on nomination (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Various articles of CA Supreme Court nomiation (Box 6, Folder 11)
- America @ Work: February 2001 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Confirmation Hearing of Hon. Carlos R. Moreno, 2001 (Box 7, Videotape 1)
- "Inside the California Supreme Court" & "The Justices of The California Supreme Court," 2006 (Box 7, Videotape 2)
- Moreno nomination to California Supreme Court, Sept. 2001 (Box 7, Videotape 3)
- Judge Moreno's Induction Ceremony, April 15, 1998 (Box 7, Videotape 4)
- Free Airtime Project 2002: Supreme Court Justice Carlos R. Moreno (Box 7, Videotape 5)
- Oral History Interview: Justice Carlos Moreno, March 20, 2003 (Box 7, Videotape 6)
- Justice Carlos Moreno speeches (Box 7, Compact disc 1)